<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of metal &amp; mineral waters viz. those of the Spaw, Bathe, Epsom, North-hall, Barnet, Tunbridge, and the new-wells at Islington. Wherein is described their bad as well as good qualities, with the danger of peoples too frequent and unadvisedly drinking them. BY E.P. M.D.</title>
            <author>Prat, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831010</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55637)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2038:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of metal &amp; mineral waters viz. those of the Spaw, Bathe, Epsom, North-hall, Barnet, Tunbridge, and the new-wells at Islington. Wherein is described their bad as well as good qualities, with the danger of peoples too frequent and unadvisedly drinking them. BY E.P. M.D.</title>
                  <author>Prat, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.B. for Randolph Tyler near Stationers-hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed E[llis]. Prat.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 and running title reads: Of the nature of medicinal waters.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Metallurgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mineral water --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT TREATISE OF <hi>Metal</hi> &amp; <hi>Mineral</hi> WATERS; <hi>VIZ.</hi> Thoſe of the <hi>Spaw, Bathe, Epſom, North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, Barnet, Tunbridge,</hi> and the <hi>New-Wells</hi> at <hi>Iſlington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is deſcribed their <hi>bad</hi> as well as <hi>good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> with the danger of Peoples too frequent- and unadviſedly Drinking them.</p>
            <q>Mirabilis in aquis Dominus.</q>
            <p>By <hi>E.P. M.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Randolph Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall</hi> 1684.
<pb facs="tcp:35472:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35472:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am not ignorant that the uſe of <hi>Metal</hi> and <hi>Mineral</hi> Waters are often preſcribed by Phyſitians againſt many Diſeaſes; as <hi>Palſies, Tremblings, Ulcers of the Stomach, Reins, Bladder and Womb, Teneſmus, deprav'd Months, Abortion,</hi> &amp;c. and though I know Sacred Writ ſays, <hi>Mirabilis eſt in aquis Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> becauſe of wonderful and almoſt divine virtues given them by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Phyſitian; for the cure of many rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious and contumacious Diſeaſes; and that as <hi>Vitruvius</hi> ſays, ther's ſeen no more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of nature than in Waters: yet I would firſt adviſe all diſeaſed Perſons, that they would not be too haſty, and run <hi>hand</hi> over <hi>head,</hi> as they ſay to drink thoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, becauſe it may be ſome of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> told them they found benefit by them, without conſulting the Phyſitian, whether they may be proper for them? forgetting the old ſaying, <hi>One man's Meat may be another's Poyſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next I would have the young Phyſitian, chiefly be prudent and cautious in preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:35472:4"/>them, and not, as too often, to ſend their Patients, after they have put them to great coſt, and wearied them with multitudes of Medicines, to the <hi>Wells,</hi> as their last re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, without conſidering the nature of the Waters or the Sick; and not to ſend the intemperate, and full of foul humours, or that have hot entrals, or that abound with ſtinking, ſharp malignant rebellious dregs, and who are full of obſtructions, the notorious Parent of moſt Diſeaſes, which are ſcarcely ever to be remov'd; For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Waters are all of hot and dry qualities; ſome more then others, as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from hot and poiſonous Minerals, as you will ſee in this Book; ſo that 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but there muſt remain an <hi>Empyreu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> or collection of filthy matter, which in an intemperate and diſpos'd body will beget a new kind of Diſeaſe, and augment the hot diſpoſition of the Stomach, Liver, and other Entrals ordain'd for nouriſhment, if there were any; and this from <hi>Hipp. de aere, aquis &amp; locis text. 13.</hi> Ariſtot. <hi>lib. 2, Meteor, c. 3.</hi> Galen. <hi>l. 1. c. 6. de ſimple facult.</hi> They may work miracles in ſome Diſeaſes, but <hi>rara non ſunt artis,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35472:4"/>and that will not warrant a dogmatical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, instituted in the ſound, ſafe and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod x doctrine of <hi>Hipp.</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly and immethodically to preſcribe them almoſt to all People and Diſeaſes; as your Diobolory, I had almoſt ſaid Diabolary Empirics, and wretches in Town do their <hi>Family</hi> Pills, their <hi>Friendly</hi> and <hi>Popular</hi> Pills.</p>
            <p>Then as for Ulcers of the Stomach, I cannot but think them improper, being too hot, as proceeding from <hi>Nitre, Sulphur, Vitriol,</hi> the laſt of which is altogether of a contrary nature to Man, as being of a poyſonous quality; as for <hi>Gold, Iron,</hi> &amp;c. the Learned <hi>Fallopius,</hi> who underſtood the nature of Waters certainly as well as any man, believes they impart not any of their quality to the Water. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Ulcers</hi> of the Reins and Blader, which, for the moſt part will admit of no cure; by reaſon of continual afflux of ſharp, watriſh humours, whereby their deterſion, and deſiccation is hindred; ſo for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the Womb, and preventing Abortion; theſe Waters are not of ſo drying force to work ſuch effects.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:5"/>
            <p>So that I cannot in reaſon ſee how theſe Waters ſhould be ſo proper for ſo many Diſeaſes for which they are extoll'd, for they are all famous for their potential, as they call it, and hidden heat, in an eminent degree, whereby they deſtroy the native oeconomy and temper of the Entrals: and imprint in them an extraneous heat, and ſo cauſe Dropſies, as <hi>Hipp.</hi> noted in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Example of his, and a <hi>1000</hi> other dire diſeaſes, which prove incurable, and haſten death.</p>
            <p>Certain it is ſome Phyſitians, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate filthy lucre, promote the Waters, and even diſcover new ones: And though many out of a good intent, in Books, extol them, yet let none precipitate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to danger of another, and perhaps worſe diſeaſe, but adviſe with the Learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:5"/>
            <head>TO His ever Honoured Friend The LADY <hi>VERE BEA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MONT,</hi> OF <hi>Grace-dieu, in Com. Leic.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>PRay be pleas'd to accept of this ſmall Preſent; but not as any the leaſt requital, I beſeech you, for the almoſt innumerable favours you have been pleas'd from time to time to conferr upon me; ſince I fear it can ſcarcely be call'd an Acknowlegment. In ſhort, Madam, this ſhort Treatiſe, is intended for public benefit in general,
<pb facs="tcp:35472:6"/>but if it may, in the leaſt meaſure, be ſerviceable or conducible towards the Preſerving of your Ladiſhips Health, in particular, I have attain'd my Aim; and in an happy hour may then ſubſcribe my ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ever oblig'd Servant,</hi> E. Prat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35472:6"/>
            <head>OF THE NATURE OF Medicinal Waters.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Matter Origine of Fountains in General.</head>
               <p>AND here I ſhall be brief; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending not a ſpeculative Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical, but a Medico-practical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for information and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the unlearn'd, and not for Learned Philoſophers and Phyſitians.</p>
               <p>Now 'tis clearly my Opinion, with the Divine <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle's</hi> Maſter, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>Thales Mileſius,</hi> as alſo <hi>Philo, lib. de mundi opificio;</hi> the great <hi>Seneca, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>queſt. natural.</hi> and others; that the Original of Fountains is from the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35472:7"/>Sea; from whence, through Sinuoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Veins and <hi>Meanders</hi> of the Earth, water is carried to certain places, where it breaks forth and continually flows; it may very probably be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectur'd they had this from the greateſt of Philoſophers <hi>Salomon,</hi> who in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.7. ſays, <hi>all Rivers run into the Sea, and it overflows not; unto the place from whence they came thither they flow again,</hi> and indeed ſcaree can there be aſſign'd any other reaſon why the Sea doth not redound by ſuch a dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and afflux of Rivers; unleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Rivers do again flow out of the Sea, and return and pay only ſo much to the Sea, as they borrowed therefrom. Although the Evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Extraction of watry Clouds by the Attractive force of the Sun, is no ſmall help: and other material helping cauſes are Rains and Snows which augment (though they do not generate) the Rivers; for theſe help being withdrawn, heat of the Sun approaching they become Rarefied and the neighbour parts of the dry'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35472:7"/>Earth drink them off. Whence <hi>Kings</hi> 17.7. the River <hi>Careth</hi> is ſaid to wax dry by reaſon of the Sun's too great heat.</p>
               <p>But we have one <hi>Cardanus</hi> impiouſly and Atheiſtically diſputing againſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, ſubtil. c.</hi> 2. <hi>de Elementis,</hi> whom we ſhall endeavour to ſatisfactorily anſwer and enervate; though God Almighty's Power and Wiſdom, might be oppos'd as anſwer enough, and Sacred Scripture ought to be of more Authority than all humane ſaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
               <p>Firſt then he ſays the Sea-water, becauſe 'tis heavy, cannot aſcend to ſuch an height, as the tops of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; but to this have been ſeveral refutations; ſome aſcribing this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the operations of the Celeſtial bodies; and they ſay this motion is not violent, (though it be contrary to the private inclination of its proper form) if the <hi>Potentia obedientialis</hi> be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; whereby inferior Bodies are made to obey their Superiors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Others ſay there is a certain inſite,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35472:8"/>attractive faculty in the Veins of the Earth, whereby it ſucks Water out of the Sea, as the Veins of Animals ſuck Blood: others there are but too long for this place, and wholly Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical and ſo not eaſily to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by ordinary capacities and ſo I omit them.</p>
               <p>Then Secondly, he ſays before the Water could reach the Mountains out of the Sea, there's no reaſon to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but it would break forth: But the Earth hath paſſages in ſome places and in ſome none. Then whatſoever he aſſigns to be the original of Fountains, it may be queried why in ſome places and Mountains there are Fountains and Rivers, and in ſome none?</p>
               <p>Then Thirdly, he ſays, if it were ſo, Rivers would never be leſs; but it may be anſwered Rivers ſometimes grow leſs from what portion is loſt which comes from falls of Showers and Snows; and when part is ſuckt up by the dryneſs of the Earth, and heat of the Sun, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, he ſays the Sea would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35472:8"/>not ſatisfy ſo many Rivers, when the greateſt part of Waters vaniſh by the heat of the Sun; But it may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that the Sea receives only as much as it gives forth; as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Rivers flow to the Sea, that they may flow out again;</hi> then if the greateſt part of Water ſhould vaniſh, the Sea would long agone have been waſted; but the extracted vapors are recondens'd into Water which either flows into the Sea, or falls upon the Earth, to augment the Rivers, which at length unburthen themſelves into the Sea.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, He ſays, there can be no reaſon given why it ſhould flow from one Mountain and not from another; But the anſwer to his ſecond Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſolves this.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He ſays, Fountains and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers would taſt ſaltiſh and brackiſh. But to this is anſwer'd that Sea-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whilſt it paſſes through various Veins, Sinews and Meanders of the Earth, and ſo being as it were ſtrein'd it ſenſibly depoſes its ſaltneſs and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs. Hence the more remote
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35472:9"/>Fountains are from the Sea, the ſweeter they are. If any ſhall ſay, that the Water was more likely to contract a bitterneſs by reaſon of the Exhalations it receives from the Earth: it may be anſwered, that they are not any ſort of Exhalations that produce bitterneſs, but only aduſt ones; and all are not ſuch in the intrals the Earth. Therefore now <hi>Cardan,</hi> we may conclude, I hope, hath not got any thing by contradicting <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Diviſion of Fountains and of Mineral and Metal Waters.</head>
               <p>HAving in the former Chapter given the Reader a plain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Matter and Origine of Fountains, we ſhould in the next place, ſee how many ſorts of Fountains there are, but becauſe 'tis the work of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophers and Hydrogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35472:9"/>and nothing of an advantage to our preſent purpoſe we ſhall whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omit it, and only ſpeak of Mineral and Metallic Fountains, as being the ſubject of our preſent Diſcourſe. Now thoſe I call Mineral and Metallic Waters, which participate of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and faculty of that Metall or Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral through which they paſs in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns and Veins of the Earth. The which are either 1 <hi>Salt,</hi> 2 <hi>Vitriol,</hi> 3 <hi>Allumn,</hi> 4 <hi>Bitumen,</hi> 5 <hi>Naptha,</hi> 6 <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</hi> 7 <hi>Gypſum,</hi> 8 <hi>Arſenic,</hi> 9 <hi>Cadmia,</hi> 10 <hi>Antimony,</hi> 11 <hi>Chryſocolla,</hi> 12 <hi>Ochre,</hi> 13 <hi>Lime,</hi> 14 <hi>Aſhes,</hi> 15 <hi>Pummice-ſtones,</hi> 16 <hi>Gold,</hi> 17 <hi>Iron,</hi> 18 <hi>Braſs,</hi> 19 <hi>Lead,</hi> 20 <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> and 21 <hi>Quickſilver.</hi> Now as I ſaid the Minerals through which Waters paſs, beſtowing upon them in their journey a conſiderable part and portion of their good and bad qualities; I thought it very requiſite, before I diſcours'd of the uſe of the Waters themſelves, to ſay ſomthing of the Natures and Properties of the Metals and Minerals they are mixt with; that thereby you may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35472:10"/>able to judge of the nature of the Waters proceeding from them; then we will begin with <hi>Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The faculties of <hi>Salt</hi> are great, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and very uſeful to man; but not ſo neceſſary in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> as many think; ſuch as your Quacking <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> who predicate many wonderful and vain ſtories of Salt reduced by their Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Art; for they audaciouſly aſſert that their is a Purgative faculty in Medicaments becauſe of Salt; and when they have got ſome Extract from any Medicament, then they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently aver that they have got its Salt forſooth; but theſe being things above the vulgar capacity; I ſhall ſay <hi>Salt</hi> is very Conſervative, of an Aſtringing, Abſterging, Purging, Diſcuſſing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, Extenuating quality, and vindicates the Body from Putrefaction; yet ſome <hi>Salt</hi> is better then others; but us'd immoderately produces very bad effects, as ſharp, ſalt corroding hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors all over the Body, Scabs, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, the Stone, and other dire Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; as Dulneſs of ſight, diſorderly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35472:10"/>Fermentations in the Blood, rendring it thick and earthy by burning it; <hi>Schroder</hi> thinks thus of the Original of <hi>Salts;</hi> the <hi>Macrocoſm</hi> he ſays, as the other two Kingdoms, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable and Animal, is ſuſteined and lives by its food; in this abounds a ſalt, anſwering to the ſalt Excrements in the Sweat, Urine, and Dejections in Animals; now the Salt of the greater World congregated into the inferior Glob, is of a dverſe kind, according to the variety of its Matrix, even as the ſalt Excrement in Animals is different; hence, <hi>Common Salt, Salt Gem, Salt Nitre, Alum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Greeks</hi> call that <hi>Calcanthum,</hi> which the <hi>Latines</hi> from its blackneſs, call <hi>Attramentum Sutorium,</hi> or <hi>Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers Ink;</hi> and from its ſpendent vitreous <hi>Nitre, Vitriol; Dioſcorides</hi> a man of profound Judgment in the <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> reckons three ſorts thereof, two Native, and one facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; one ſort of the Native is found concreted in the bowels of the Earth; another is collected in form of a Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35472:11"/>out of ſome Mine, which put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Veſſel ſoon coagulates into <hi>Vitriol;</hi> as for the factitious we have nothing to ſay to that here: the Native or Foſſile <hi>Vitriol</hi> participates of <hi>Calcitis, Miſy,</hi> and <hi>Sory;</hi> the Native and White is prefer'd in the Medicinal uſes; which the <hi>Metallicolous Alchymiſts</hi> ſay is produc'd by their <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury;</hi> as of Sperm; which they indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminately exhibit to all affections, out of which they draw a certain acid Liquor, a few drops whereof mix'd with Syrup of <hi>Violets,</hi> acquire a moſt elegant colour and taſte: But Oyl of <hi>Sulphur</hi> will do the ſame, and a few drops of one or both of them inſuſed in the Syrup of <hi>Roſes,</hi> will make the whole Liquor red; which they call, forſooth, Tincture of <hi>Roſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Nature 'tis true hath enrich'd <hi>Vitriol</hi> with eximious faculties, which skilful Phyſitians have both experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd and left deſcrib'd; as <hi>Galen, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorides, Paulus Aegineta, Aetius, Oriba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> &amp;c. who have very much nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litated it: it heats, binds, drys, kills
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35472:11"/>broad Worms, helps againſt Toad poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, preſerves moiſt fleſh, and drys up humors, drives away Putrifaction, robo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the inward parts: outwardly it binds, purges Ulcers, cauſes Wrincles like <hi>Alum,</hi> with whom it hath relation; But beſides theſe excellent qualities <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol</hi> hath alſo its bad ones: for it is ill for the Stomach, acrimonious, corroſive and vomitous, and therefore ignorant <hi>Quackſalvers</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> give it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in <hi>Wine,</hi> and ſometimes in <hi>Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water</hi> in uncertain weight, againſt <hi>Quotidian</hi> and <hi>Quartane Agues,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Diſeaſes, and indeed the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is often reſolv'd by vehement Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, but this Medicine being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully Adminiſtred proves moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more formidable than the Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alum</hi> is, as it were, the Brine of the Earth; whereof <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> makes three ſorts; the Round, the Liquid, and the Jagged, or Sciſſile, the laſt is often call'd Plumeous, for they are ſo like in form that they can ſcarſe be diſtinguiſh'd, yet they differ both in nature and qualities, for the Sciſſile is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35472:12"/>manifeſtly binding, and may be burnt, but the other is Acrimonious, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not by fire. <hi>Mathiolus,</hi> ſays he ſaw and taſted a Liquid <hi>Alum;</hi> of which he aſſerts, that he never found any thing more Aſtrictive. Now when <hi>Alum</hi> is ſimply mention'd, we mean <hi>Roch-Alum,</hi> which is a ſaltneſs of a Mineral Earth, of a Leadiſh nature, conſiſting of an acid ſpirit, and a cauſtick Earthy ſalt; and all <hi>Alum</hi> is of Craſs parts, binds much; whence 'tis call'd <hi>Stypterion</hi> in <hi>Greek,</hi> becauſe it is Styp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, it heats, cleanſes, amends putrid Ulcers, dryes humid ones, abſumes ſuperfluous fleſh, takes away itching, cures the Scab, and very uſeful in many Medicaments made for the Cure of Ulcers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bitumen,</hi> which the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaltes,</hi> is as it were the fatneſs of the Earth ſwiming above the Waters, which being caſt upon the ſhoar, thickens and becomes hard, tenacious and inflamable: As long as it ſwims on the water 'tis ſoft, but when 'tis off it becomes thicker and harder, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35472:12"/>reſembles dry Pitch; yet eaſily mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the fire. Many Lakes are bitumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, but eſpecially one in <hi>India,</hi> thence call'd <hi>Aſphalites,</hi> and the dead Sea, becauſe of its vaſtneſs, and becauſe its Water remains almoſt immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; not ſtormy, but heavy, ſalt, thick, and ſtinking; wherein neither Plants nor Animals breed; neither doth it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſuch as are put into it, or admit them into its bowels.</p>
               <p>All <hi>Bitumen</hi> is not ſolid and hard; but ſome is perpetually fluid and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, call'd <hi>Naptha;</hi> which is the ſtreining of <hi>Babylonian Bitumen,</hi> white of colour, and moſt capacious of Fire; for Fire and this are ſo near a kin, that it will preſently leap into it, when near it. There is alſo black <hi>Bitumen.</hi> For its Virtues all <hi>Bitumen</hi> diſcuſſes, mollifies, glutinates, defends from inflammation, by olfaction, ſuffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migation, or impoſition; mends the ſtrangling of the Womb. <hi>Naptha</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuates, incides, digeſts, penetrates, abſumes frigid and thick humors in all, parts of the Body, and cures the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35472:13"/>Reſolution of the Norues, Palſies, and diſeaſes in the Veins and Arteries from cold cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nitre</hi> of the ſame nature with the <hi>Salts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gypſum,</hi> is a kind of <hi>Talk,</hi> of the nature of <hi>Lime,</hi> whoſe hot, fiery, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic quality every one knows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratsbane,</hi> or <hi>Arſenic,</hi> is between a <hi>Salt</hi> and a <hi>Sulphur,</hi> 'tis of ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimonious, corroding, hot quality, that it will burn to a cruſt; diſſolving, deſtroying and preying upon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Life; malignant, and an Enemy to all Natural parts; and to the Radidical moiſture, and innate heat; and therefore was very ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd of <hi>Nich. Alexanarinus</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it for an Ingredient in the great <hi>Athanaſia,</hi> ſays the great man of skill in the <hi>Materia Medica, Johannes Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus;</hi> for by permixtion with other Medicaments it doth not depoſe its malignity. The Learned <hi>Schroder</hi> ſays 'tis one of the higheſt Poyſons; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides its acrimony, it is an Enemy to our Natural Balſam of Life, ſo that it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35472:13"/>brings ſtrange ſymptoms, not only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken inwardly, but apply'd outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as Convulſions, numneſs of Hands and Feet, cold Sweats, Palpitations, Faintings, Vomitings, Corroſions and Torments, Thirſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cadmia,</hi> Metallic, 'tis the Stone out of which <hi>Braſs</hi> is drawn, and is call'd <hi>Braſs-Ore,</hi> which Artificers uſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Yellow <hi>Braſs,</hi> which the Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men call <hi>Aurichalcum,</hi> or <hi>Orichalcum,</hi> and 'tis probable this is the Stone which <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> calls, <hi>Didachos,</hi> or the Devils-ſtone: <hi>Cadmia</hi> diſiccates gently, abſterges and helps humid and putrid Ulcers, and draws them to ſcars; <hi>Schroder</hi> ſays 'tis Cauſtic, and that it ulcerates the Hands and Feet of the <hi>Miners,</hi> and taken inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kills all Creatures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antimony,</hi> or <hi>Stibium,</hi> or the ſeventh Metall, which ſome ſay is <hi>Mercury,</hi> others <hi>Ambar,</hi> but neither of theſe are more than in a potency to be Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls; a grand <hi>Alchymiſtical Quackſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Idol;</hi> the ſole Empyrical, Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Cathartic; whereby they boaſt to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35472:14"/>cure all Diſeaſes; but it moſt devilſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſturbs mens Ventricles by moving upwards and downwards; others it miſerably torments by vigorous Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſome it kills and reſtores very few to perfect health. One <hi>Cornelius Gemma,</hi> a Phyſitian of <hi>Lovain,</hi> relates, how a <hi>Paracelſian</hi> Engliſh <hi>Quackſalver,</hi> being himſelf and his Wife ſick of a Fever, took himſelf and gave to his Wife, that which they call prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Antimony,</hi> whereupon ſhe fell quickly diſtracted, and changed her Life, yet valid, with death; and he complaining of Dreams and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Watchings, ſeven days after his Dejection, began to Rave; from that he became Epileptical; from his Epilepſie he fell into a Lethargy, being therewithal ſomewhat Apople<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical: when he had been three days in that ſopor, he fell again to his raving, and was ſo agitated with fury, that not long after he expir'd and paſs'd from his conjugal Bed to his conjugal Tomb: and howſoever the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> cry up their Preparations of <hi>Antimony,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35472:14"/>yet as able Phyſitians as any in the World forbear to exhibit them becauſe they have much better Medicaments wherewith they may more ſecurely cure any Diſeaſe. And I could give a large account of the diſmal Accidents that I have known happen by the adminiſtring of <hi>Antimony:</hi> and my ever honoured Maſter Dr. <hi>Patin, Regins Profeſſor</hi> in Phyſick in the Famous Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> wrote a Book which he call'd the Martyrology of <hi>Antimony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſocolle,</hi> which the Shopmen, following the <hi>Barbarous Mauritanian Idiome</hi> call it <hi>Borax,</hi> is found in the <hi>Golden, Silver,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> Mines in <hi>Armenia, Macedonia,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus;</hi> it heats, checks ſuperſluous fleſh, and is mordacious; it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Ulcers to ſanity, but taken at the Mouth 'tis perillous, ſays <hi>Renodeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ochre.</hi> is a kind of Yellow Earth much commended in <hi>Affrica,</hi> not lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous, but friable, clayey and ſinooth, it binds, corrodes, diſcuſſes Tumors, and repreſſes Excreſcences.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35472:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gold,</hi> is the greateſt Cordial in the Pocket; moſt certainly; for <hi>omne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacum debet eſſe Bumidum &amp; Calidum: au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum autem eſt frigidum &amp; ſicum, i.e.</hi> every Cordial ought to be moiſt and hot, but <hi>Gold</hi> is cold and dry, <hi>Ergo</hi> Gold is no Cordial at all; and nothing indeed is Cordial but what nouriſhes; a Glaſs of generous <hi>Wine,</hi> and nouriſhing Broaths, and ſuch Diet are the greateſt Cordials under the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iron</hi> is an ignoble Metal, conſiſting of <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Sulphur,</hi> not ſo meltable, cruder, or rather of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Salt;</hi> mixed with the Cruder parts of the Earth: it binds and opens, as the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> ſays; the opening Virtue is chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in its more Volatile part, and ſo in the <hi>Salt;</hi> the Aſtringent virtue lyes in the more fixed part, and ſo in the Earthy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Braſs,</hi> was formerly dedicated to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> from her <hi>Iſland Cyprus</hi> where great plenty was dug; 'tis either of a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den color call'd <hi>Aurichalcum;</hi> or red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and then call'd <hi>Braſs</hi> abſolutely. <hi>Braſs</hi> was of more uſe among the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35472:15"/>Antients, than either <hi>Gold, Silver</hi> or <hi>Iron;</hi> for the firſt money was <hi>Braſs;</hi> and hence we meet with <hi>Aerarium, publicum, Aes ali num, Queſtor aerarius,</hi> their Warlike Arms alſo were not of <hi>Iron</hi> or <hi>Steel,</hi> but <hi>Braſs</hi> as alſo their Statues and Temple doors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Load,</hi> according to the <hi>Alchymiſts,</hi> is both dedicated to <hi>Saturn</hi> and called <hi>Saturn,</hi> and in their opinion 'tis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated of impure <hi>Quickſilver,</hi> and a little impure <hi>Sulphur,</hi> and 'tis thought that not only under the Earth, but in the open Air alſo it angments, and therefore <hi>Cardanus,</hi> thinks it endamages houſes by its weight: for its Virtues, it refrigerates, binds, and thickens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foſſile</hi> or Native <hi>Sulphur</hi> is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly generated out of a certain fat por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Earth; much whereof is in <hi>Lipara, Melos,</hi> and ſuch like places, it is much in quality a kin to fire, for if be caſt upon Coals it will burn, and not be extinguiſhed, till all its oleous and fat ſubſtance be waſted; that <hi>Sulphur</hi> whereof your <hi>Quacking Chymiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35472:16"/>tell many vain and ridiculous ſtories, is not common <hi>Sulphur;</hi> yet 'tis mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though they aſſert it to be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of mixture. But no more of that here. It heats, cooles, reſolves, cures Coughs, and difficulty of breathing, taken in an Egg, or burnt and its ſmoak catch'd, moves Spittle: mixed with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Swines greaſe, it mittigates and kills the Itch over the whole Body; and mixed with <hi>Turpentine</hi> it cures Tetters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> or <hi>Quickſilver</hi> is the prime Idol of the <hi>Alchymists,</hi> which they pronounce to be the principle of things and Sperm of Metals; and indeed ſo true each, that nothing more falſe; for if Metalls have any Sperm, 'tis within themſelves, not elſe where to be ſought; nor will ever mixt bodies naturally reſolve themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Salt, Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> though theſe <hi>Chymical Vulcans</hi> will be ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering them out, as the Learned Philoſopher and Phyſitian <hi>Riolanus</hi> hath proved againſt them. This <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver</hi> its as it were, the Monſter of Nature, which will not be ſubject to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35472:16"/>Natures Laws; 'tis more fluxible than <hi>Water,</hi> more permeable than <hi>Vinegar;</hi> tho it moiſtens not; ſometimes cures cold diſeaſes; ſometimes hot: when it ſeems cold it induces hot effects; when hot then cold ones; it ſometimes hurts in ſmall quantities, always in great; it eaſily loſes it proper form, and eaſily reaſſumes it; and in this 'tis miraculous, that it often profits being taken inwardly; and often cauſes Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, trembling and other ſad effects when apply'd outwardly; <hi>Falop. de Lue Vener.</hi> 'tis ſuch a Beaſt that can ſcarce be tam'd by any Art; So that <hi>Galen</hi> the Prince of Phyſitians, next <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> durſt not uſe it; having learn'd of <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> that it was Poyſonous. Its qualities are yet under debate; for ſome, from its effects, ſay 'tis cold; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as <hi>Avicen</hi> whom <hi>Palmarius</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers follow, ſay 'tis cold and moiſt; <hi>Fracaſtorius, Tomitanus</hi> and others, who attribute a corroding faculty to it, contend for its heat. But <hi>Renodeus,</hi> with <hi>Trajanus,</hi> thinks it to be of a mixt quality, participating of many other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35472:17"/>faculties, but conſiſting chiefly of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile parts; for it incides, attenuates, penetrates, melts, reſolves, looſens the belly; and what is moſt to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, partly by an attractive quality at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts humors from the ſuperficies to the Centre; and excludes them by ſtool; and partly by an impulſive faculty, them from the Centre to the habit, and ejects them by ſalivation; and it often works by feige when it ſhould ſalivate; and ofetn ſalivates when it ſhould move downward. Thus much of the nature of all the Metalls and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals from whence the Waters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, now a few words concerning the manner have the Waters acquire their virtues from them.</p>
               <p>Now all theſe Waters are of a mixt, not ſimple nature, for they proceed and paſs not from and through one Quarry or Vein of the Earth only but from divers; and therefore acquire diverſe faculties according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſubſtances which they draw along with them: as for Example, if a Water ariſes where is generated a Quarry or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35472:17"/>Vein of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> from whence it paſſes where <hi>Iron</hi>'s generated, or <hi>Lead;</hi> this Water more certainly ſhall acquire mixt faculties to it ſelf; and yet it ſhall attract more of the ſubſtance of the one than the other, according as any one quality makes more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion than another: and many times ſo comes to paſs that the Water pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from and paſſages through paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges where the Metall or Mineral is not yet perfectly generated, then you muſt expect it to be of an hot Nature, but not ſo much participating of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or Mineral; the reaſon is becauſe all Metalls and Minerals have heat for their efficient cauſe, and therefore if the Waters paſs by while the Metall or Mineral is in generating, and where there is the cauſe of their generation, which is heat, they will conſequently become hot; whence they will prove to be actually hot, and of a firery qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and this ſhall be more or leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the more or leſſer acting of of the Heat; or by reaſon of the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or ſhorter ſtay of the Water, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35472:18"/>by reaſon of the nature, quality and ſubſtance of the Matter which is more or leſs permiſcible. For that the Waters do effectually attract the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Quarry or Vein, there are three things requiſite <hi>(viz.)</hi> that heat perfom it parts well; that it acts op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely, and thoſe things which ought to be mixt, be fit to be mixt. So that ſince theſe three conditions are required to the compleating the work; it comes ſo to paſs that although Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do ſometimes participate of more Quarries or Veins; yet it ſhall retain the faculties of one more than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; either by reaſon of one of theſe cauſes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> either becauſe heat was more active, or from its longer ſtay, or from the Matters being more apt, or laſtly from all theſe cauſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct. Now a Quarry or Vein doth not impart its ſubſtance or faculties to the Water one manner of way only; but either it ſo imparts it, as its ſubſtance, is truly and really mixt, with its and thoſe Waters and reteins their facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for a long time and to ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35472:18"/>or elſe they are mixt not with a true and real mixture, but are only confounded; and when they are mixt by ſuch a kind of confuſion, the Waters of the Quarry are not all one, neither are they truly mixt, for one may ſeparate one from another: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times laſtly they are mixt, not becauſe of the ſubſtance of the Quarry is mixt with Water; but only vapors elevated from the matter are permixt; And ſince it happens as you may underſtand that mixtion is perform'd by theſe three manner of ways, 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if Water mixing it ſelf in ſeveral Veins, ſhall attract and contract to it ſelf the faculty of one more than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As for example; if Water that ſhall be perfectly mixt in one Quarry, with another confuſedly only, and with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, with the vapors only, and not with the ſubſtance, it ſhall retein much more of the nature of that wherewith it is perfectly mixt, than the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35472:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Waters <hi>of Bath,</hi> and their Cauſes.</head>
               <p>COncerning which there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe divers opinions: Now theſe Waters being of ſo hot a Nature, that throw but a Fowl therein and it ſhall immediately deplume it; put Fiſh and Eggs therein and it will preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct them; that theſe Waters are ſo hot of their own nature, I cannot believe; for all Water is always, and of its own Nature cold in quality; and if it become hot by accident take but away the heating cauſe thereof, and it ſhall return to its preſtine cold temper of its own accord, without any thing of an altering nature being adhibited: For there are Rivers in hot Countries that are not very hot from the heat of the Sun: So that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude theſe Waters to be hot in the Caverns of the Earth from an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35472:19"/>cauſe: which that it may be made more plainly manifeſt, we ſhall briefly inſpect into the cauſes of Baths.</p>
               <p>Concerning their efficient Cauſes their are likewiſe various opinions; omitting the whimſical frothy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the <hi>Chymiſts;</hi> let us ſee what the more ſound and ſolid ſort of Learned Philoſophers ſay to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſome aſcribe this virtue to the Rays of the Sun with <hi>Thermophilus,</hi> who held that the Sun penetrating the pores of the Earth (for certainly the Earth is porous and Spungy,) was in its bowels there fortified, and made more active in heat; ſo that like Fire it heats Water, and what ever it meets with, and even burns what it meets with combuſtible; but if this were ſo, theſe Baths would be ſo hot in Summer only, not in Winter; or at leaſt it would follow that theſe Springs would be leſs hot in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than in Summer, contrary to all experience; for every Idiot can tell you the Springs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are hotter in <hi>Winter</hi> than <hi>Summer,</hi> the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35472:20"/>of the Learned Philoſophers aſcribe to that they call <hi>Antiperiſtaſis,</hi> that is, in plain Engliſh; the Earth is hotter within in <hi>Winter</hi> when the Sun's abſent, than in Summer; and ſo they'll tell you that their Sellars are hot in <hi>Winter</hi> and cold in <hi>Summer.</hi> Secondly, I cannot conceive how the Sun ſhould penetrate into ſuch deep Caverns of the Earth as, by force of its heat, to make the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters therein to become ſo hot; where we ſee, it cannot effect the ſame on Lakes in any hot Region: Then 3ly, We know that there are Baths found in the moſt cold Countrys, as <hi>Iſlind,</hi> &amp;c-Some with <hi>Mileus</hi> will have a Wind or a Spirit vehemently toſs'd and mov'd up and down, and ſo penn'd up grows hot, and ſo coming to fall upon the Waters overheats them. <hi>Democritus</hi> ſays, they receive their heat from <hi>Aſhes</hi> and <hi>Lime:</hi> others think theſe Waters grow hot by reaſon of vehement mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and beating againſt the Rocks; and not a few there are which ſay that the matter through which they paſs heats them, which they ſay is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35472:20"/>that ſome ſmell ſo ſtrongly of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,</hi> becauſe they flow from Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phury Veins. Others, o'th other ſide, will have the cauſe to be an extream heat within the Earth in thoſe places, which overflow with hot Waters; and Learned Dr. <hi>Jordan</hi> our Countryman if I miſtake not, thinks they derive their heat from the ſermentation of Metals in their Generation; to which is required an actual heat with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain humidity; and ſome affirm that Thunder heats the Waters, as may be ſeen from <hi>Manlius;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Suni autem cunctis permixti partibus ignes,</l>
                     <l>Qui gravidas habitant fabricantes fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na nubes,</l>
                     <l>Hac penetrant Terras, Aethnamque imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur Olympo,</l>
                     <l>Et calidas reddunt ipſis in fontibus undas.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> will have the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to wax hot from a mutual combat and conflict of divers <hi>Salts</hi> or Mineral bodies; after the ſame manner, as we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35472:21"/>ſee in the conjunction of Spirit of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol</hi> or Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> as from the two fires the Glaſs becomes ſo hot,
<q>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t multo accenſis, fervore exuberat undis, Clauſus ubi exuſto liquor indignatur abeno.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now among ſo many diſagreeing opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, when there can be but one ith' right on't; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the great ſearcher into the Secrets of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in my opinion hit the Nail o'th head, who following <hi>Empedoeles,</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> when he ſaw theſe <hi>Therm</hi> or Baths, ſo call'd from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Calidus,</hi> to be ſo hot, thought they could become ſo no other way, than from a moſt fervent cauſe, becauſe all Waters of their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are cold, and could think the efficient cauſe to be no other then Fire included in the inmoſt parts of the Earth, and there, as it were, primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neally reſiding; of which the <hi>Epicure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Poet and Philoſopher,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35472:21"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Principio t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llus habet in Corpora prima,</l>
                     <l>Unde mare immenſum, vo ventes flumina fontes</l>
                     <l>Aſſidur revomunt habet ignes unde ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur,</l>
                     <l>Nam multis ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>enſa locis ardent ſola Terrae.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now that there is Fire under the Earth, beſides the hot fiery water Springs; the <hi>Lime, Aſhes,</hi> &amp;c. which are vomited and dug out of the Earth, may confirme and perſuade us; as being the genuine effects of fire; to ſay nothing of Smoak and Soot, breaking out of the Earth; and in ſome places fire it ſelf; therefore Subterranean fire, which <hi>Kirkerus</hi> calls <hi>pyrophylacia, i. e.</hi> a Priſon for Fire, is the moſt certain cauſe of the heat of the Waters, For while thoſe Springs of Waters upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, are carryed by the Veins and Sinewy bendings of Metalls, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Dragons and Chaldrons in the Baths of the Antients, writhed and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35472:22"/>twiſted with circles of <hi>Braſs;</hi> like a Meander; and from thence artract the Virtues and Vices, as I may ſo ſay, of Metalls, wherewith the Water is tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctur'd, they wax hot from the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fire Subterraneous to thoſe wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, even juſt as Water in a Pot is heat by Fire; and <hi>Bartholine</hi> ſays expreſly, that Fire doth not heat the Water af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner above related from <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Empedocles;</hi> but that the Pipes or Veins of the Earth contein Fire it ſelf within them,</p>
               <p>Now the VVater becomes more or leſs hot, here and there, Firſt, as the matter is found more or leſs apt for heat; Secondly, as that Fire is nigher or farther off the VVater; whence in ſome places Fire breaks out together with VVaters, in ſome places VVater without Fire to be ſeen. Thirdly, as there is a preſent quantity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of matter, as for example, a great quantity of VVater would extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh a little Fire, ſo that we ſee no Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ſo hot, much leſs a Lake, leaſt of all the Sea.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35472:22"/>
               <p>But ſince ſo much and laſting a Fire cannot continue without ſome food, or maintenance, therefore it muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily have ſome <hi>Matter</hi> to nouriſh and renew it. Now this matter muſt be ſomething that will burn, either dry, or oleagenous. Lands taken from the Fens and dryed, they call it roaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, cannot be the fires continual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for it is ſoon conſum'd by the Fire, and it burns only by reaſon of the Roots and Herbs and Graſs which it contains; wherefore it muſt be oyly, fat matter; Now the fatty things which are begot in the Bowels of the Earth, are chiefly <hi>Marle, Bitumen</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone;</hi> now <hi>Marle</hi> burns not, nor any Earth, unleſs it be Sulphurous, or Bituminous; ſo that we may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude that <hi>Bitumen</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone</hi> and <hi>Oyls</hi> are the material cauſe of the hot Baths: hence Baths are call'd Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, becauſe they abound with <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,</hi> with which the Ancients us'd to exprate their offences, whence the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> call it <hi>Theion, i. e., Divine;</hi> For whatſoever is annointed with <hi>Oyl</hi> or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35472:23"/>
                  <hi>Bitumen</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> it preſently takes fire: For moiſt and fatty, by conſent of the Philoſophers, is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine food of Fire;</p>
               <p>As for the nature of our Baths in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> Phyſitians are divided among themſelves, ſome ſaying one thing and ſome another: Dr. <hi>Turner,</hi> who hath wrote concerning them, ſays they conſiſt of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Copper</hi> mixt together: Dr. <hi>Joràan</hi> and Dr. <hi>Venner,</hi> Practitioners at the <hi>Bath,</hi> will have them impregnated with <hi>Sulphur, Nitre,</hi> and <hi>Bitumen,</hi> Dr. <hi>Venner</hi> becauſe he judges <hi>Sulphur</hi> to have the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but Dr. <hi>Jordan</hi> is for <hi>Bitumen.</hi> Others will have them conſiſt of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as <hi>Loſſius,</hi> who in his counſel concerning theſe Baths, when he had given his opinion, that the material cauſe of Baths in general was <hi>Sulphur, Oyl</hi> and <hi>Bitumen;</hi> tells you afterwards that the <hi>Baths</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> contein neither <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> nor <hi>Bitumen;</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither taſte nor ſmell of either, and ſays if you diſtill them in a Glaſs Alembec, you will not find the leaſt ſign
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35472:23"/>of either, but a certain ſubſtance like <hi>Salt,</hi> ſuch as is found in Pipes, through which Water runs into Cyſterns; and this he takes to he a kind of Nitre, wherewith that ground be ſays doth much abound; mixt with a portion of <hi>Vitriol:</hi> and the Learned Dr. <hi>Meara,</hi> in a Letter to Dr. <hi>Prujean,</hi> (before <hi>Loſſius</hi> wrote) concerning the cauſe of the Heat in theſe Waters, tells him; as a certain perſon of Quality was riding out of the City one day to take the Air; he by chance eſpies a certain kind of Chalk, or Marie as white as Snow ſpringing out of the Earth like Mole-hills, brings ſome of it home and ſhews it to him and Dr. <hi>Maplet;</hi> which he ſays, was of a crumbling nature, and almoſt turning to Powder of its own accord; affording a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ſharp, ſowr taſte without aſtriction; but biting; and begetting an inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory choking or ſtopping in the Throat; that he did not doubt, but that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded with much <hi>Vitriol,</hi> and that it was not altogether void of <hi>Arſnic:</hi> put into cold water, it preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35472:24"/>an ebullition, as if it had been <hi>Quicks Lime,</hi> and the water by degrees grew vehemently hot; and ſince this <hi>Marle</hi> or <hi>Chalk</hi> was found in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring parts of <hi>Bath,</hi> he very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably was induc'd to believe that the <hi>Bath</hi> water grew hot from this Fire. And he ſays, though he is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that Authors every where aſcribe the heat of the <hi>Bath</hi> waters to <hi>Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> and <hi>Bitumen;</hi> and though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd but that there is great plenty of <hi>Bitumen</hi> in thoſe Springs, and that they are abundantly impregnated therewith, as the Cure of Scabs, Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, Ulcers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may convince, yet he doubts whether either of them has the nature of a Ferment apt to heat the Waters; ſince both are deſtitute of <hi>Acidity,</hi> the chief promoter of <hi>Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> neither can either of them, caſt into water, produce Fermentation or Heat, and whenas they are of a clammy conſiſtence, and eſpecially the <hi>Bitumen,</hi> ſo that the Water cannot inſinuate or penetrate it ſelf into their particles, it muſt be concluded that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35472:24"/>they are unapt for ſuch a Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whenas the contrary is ſeen in that crumbly, powdry and not gummy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of the <hi>Marle:</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes leaving it wholly to Dr. <hi>Prujean</hi> to be judge, in ſo obſcure a caſe. And I likewiſe ſhall not trouble the Reader, with tedious Philoſophical diſputes upon this ſubject; being as I told thee at firſt, I intended a plain and practical, and not an hard, difficult contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive diſcourſe, and ſo ſhall paſs on in the next Chapter to ſhew you the uſe of theſe and other Waters, or as I may ſay, their Virtues and Vices. But ſomething firſt of the preparing the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the manner of preparing the Body of ſuch as intend to drink the Waters.</head>
               <p>BUt moſt Peoples intention of going to the Waters being as I ſuppoſe to cleanſe their Bodies, and free them
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35472:25"/>from Obſtructions, Stone and Gravel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and put their Bodies in good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and order; I would adviſe them by all means to Prepare and Purge their Bodies before they take any of theſe Waters, either <hi>Tunbridge, Empſom, Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> or any other hereabouts, or at other places, as likewiſe at the <hi>Bath, &amp;c.</hi> for if they go thither with groſs, foul Bodies, and gorge themſelves with the VVaters before they have unload<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en themſelves, of their overfulneſs of Blood, or bad humours, they had better ſtay at home, than to make work for the Phyſitian and damnifie themſelves in Body and Purſe.</p>
               <p>Now if thou art troubled with too much blood, which thou mayſt know by the fulneſs of the Veins, and heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and dulneſs of thy Body, thou hadſt beſt take away ſome blood, to the quantity of 6, 9, 12, ounces according to the ſtrengh of thy body, age, ſex, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or thou mayſt do it at twice; then Purge with this or the like. Take from half an ounce to an ounce of the beſt <hi>Sena,</hi> and from a Scruple to a dram of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35472:25"/>
                  <hi>Cream</hi> of <hi>Tartar,</hi> &amp; infuſe them all night in ſome <hi>White-wine</hi> or <hi>Ale</hi> Poſſet-drink ſtrein it &amp; drink it off early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or thou mayſt have Electuaries or Pills at the Apothecaries; if thou hadſt rather; a Scruple of Stomach Pills ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at night going to bed, or after thy firſt ſleep will work finely the next morning, made into three or four Pills, and you may go about your lawful occaſions: or <hi>Lenitive Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Catholicon,</hi> and <hi>Diaprunes</hi> of each two drams taken after the ſame manner, then you may venture to drink the VVaters, any of theſe taken twice firſt.</p>
               <p>If thou beeſt of a <hi>Choleric</hi> nature pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy body, by boyling ſome <hi>Sorrel, Borage, Bugloſs, Chichory, Dandelion, Endive, Strawberry-leaves, Spinach,</hi> and ſuch like in Fountain water or River water, with a little <hi>French, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and <hi>Liquorice,</hi> and ſtrein it and drink thereof for a day or two; if thou wouldſt have it pleaſant, add ſome Syrup of <hi>Violets</hi> or <hi>Lemons,</hi> and then Purge with <hi>Sena</hi> and <hi>Cream</hi> or <hi>Chriſtal</hi> of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35472:26"/>
                  <hi>Tartar</hi> the quantity as before, infus'd in ſome of the Liquor you prepared your body with, or the <hi>Electuary</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, not <hi>Pills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Melancholly</hi> abound, prepare thy body, by boyling <hi>Fumitory, Balm, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-hair, Dodder of Time, Ceterach, Hyſſop, Scabious, Agrimony,</hi> ſome of theſe, or ſuch like, as before with the Roots of <hi>Smallage, Fennel, Parſley, Polypody, Butchers-Broome, Enulacam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane, Orice,</hi> and the like, and Syrup of <hi>Maiden-hair, Apples,</hi> five opening Roots, or ſuch like: then Purge with the <hi>Decoction</hi> of <hi>Epithymum,</hi> at the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> or with <hi>Sena</hi> infus'd as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or the <hi>Electuaries,</hi> not <hi>Pills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Phlegm</hi> abound, Prepare thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with <hi>Wormwood, Southernwood, Mugwort, Agrimony, Betony, Centaury, Calamint, Majoram, Motherwort, Peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royal, Horehounà, Sage, Savory,</hi> and ſuch like, in whoſe <hi>Decoction</hi> you may infuſe <hi>Sena</hi> as before with <hi>Cream</hi> or <hi>Chriſtal</hi> of <hi>Tartar;</hi> and in lieu of the <hi>Electuaries</hi> uſe the <hi>Pills.</hi> Now for the manner of uſing the VVaters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:35472:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the time, manner and order of taking the Metallic and Mineral and <hi>Bath</hi> Waters, and other ſuch like.</head>
               <p>AS for the <hi>Time</hi> then, that is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold here; of the Year, and of the day: <hi>(proſint; Temporibus Medicina valet data tempore Et data non apto tempore vina nocent.</hi> for the Seaſon of the Year, <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> is the beſt, when the weather is commonly ſettled, warm and dry, and ſo they are commonly ordered to be taken in the Dog days;
<q>Cum canis arentes findit hiulcus agros.</q> but there are other times in <hi>Summer</hi> certainly as fit as that (for the Dog-days keep not always to one temper) as <hi>June</hi> and beginning of <hi>July,</hi> and after the Dog-days, many years are ſeaſonable, as the Seaſon falls out; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35472:27"/>in general when the weather is clear, hot and dry, the Water is beſt; as well in <hi>Winter</hi> as in <hi>Summer;</hi> nay the VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the ſtronger in hard, froſty wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the cold hindring the Spirits from evaporating; for in Rainy or Miſty weather, when <hi>Jupiter</hi> doth, <hi>per cribrum mingere,</hi> piſs through a Sieve, as <hi>Aristophanes</hi> merrily ſpeaks, the Waters muſt certainly loſe much of their Virtue.</p>
               <p>Then as to the time of the day, the Morning about an hour after <hi>Sun</hi>-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is the fitteſt; for when the Sun begins to get power, it certainly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts ſome of the Spirits of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſo conſequently not ſo ſtrong; and then is the beſt walking.</p>
               <p>Now as to the manner and order; 'tis beſt taking the quantity you are to take that day, within as ſmall a ſpace of time, as conveniently you can, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out oppreſſing the Stomach; then you ſhall take a gentle walk before you Drink, ſo as to warm your blood a little, not to ſweat or be ready to ſweat, and ſo between every Glaſs.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:35472:27"/>
               <p>Next as to the <hi>Quantity</hi> of Water to be taken every Morning, it cannot be juſtly defin'd or preſcrib'd; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the difference of bodies as to their Age, Sex, Strength, and other circumſtances; in which you are wholly to be ordered by your Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; for though the drinking of the Waters be a <hi>Quackſalving, Empyrical</hi> Remedy, yet it ought not ſo to be uſed or adminiſtred; and every one ought to remember, that the beſt direction is from thoſe things that help and hurt: ſome may begin the firſt Morning with three pints, or two quarts, or five pints, and ſo augment a pint, till they come to four Quarts, more or leſs as they find agree with their body and ſo decreaſe a pint by degrees. 'Tis not good to drink like ſome,
<q>Invenies illic qui Neſtoris ebibit annos.</q> three hundred ounces, according to <hi>Neſtor's</hi> years: Some between every glaſs eat a few <hi>Carraway,</hi> or <hi>Corriander</hi> Seed Comfeits, or Candid <hi>Elecampane,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35472:28"/>or <hi>Angelica,</hi> or <hi>Orange, Lemon,</hi> or <hi>Citron</hi> pills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And certainly 'tis very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that they ſhould have ſome <hi>Electuary, Powder</hi> or <hi>Lozenge,</hi> or ſuch like, (appropriated to the grief for which they take the Waters) appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them by their Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>Having drank your dayly quantity of Water, you will do well to walk, or ſtir up and down, and compoſe your ſelf to Mirth with ſome of the Company; for all cares and contrary paſſions of the Mind and Melancholly muſt be left behind: this done, in the Name of God go to your Dinner; if you perceive the Waters to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted and paſt through. Now the ſign of their concoction is, that your Urine begins to be colour'd; which if you perceive not you may abſtein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while longer. If you drink the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cold, take not any more after the firſt draught till that be warmed in your Stomach, and no heavineſs be perceiv'd.</p>
               <p>Now the Waters taken in ſo great a a quantity will force themſelves a way
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35472:28"/>either by Seige or Urine, yet ſome add opening Syrups as of <hi>Maidenhair,</hi> &amp;c. or of <hi>Limons,</hi> or looſening ones; or <hi>Salt,</hi> or <hi>Manna,</hi> and Purging Powders; 'tis better to drink them at the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, than ſome miles off; Then as for the time of ſtaying to drink the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, if you ask me how long it muſt be? Truly I muſt anſwer it cannot be exactly defin'd or order'd; ſome ſtay longer, ſome ſhorter time, ſome a fortnight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome a month, ſome more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Dyet to be obſerv'd by thoſe that drink the Metallic and Mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and for all other perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</head>
               <p>BY Dyet here I do not mean only <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo taken by the vulgar; for with Phyſitians it hath a larger accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; as comprehending, <hi>Air, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35472:29"/>and Reſt, things reteined and avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Sleeping and Waking, and the Paſſions of the Mind:</hi> all theſe are to be duly and rightly order'd and obſerv'd, as moſt conſiderably conducing both to the preſerving and reſtoring of health.</p>
               <p>To begin then with the <hi>Air;</hi> now whereever you drink the Waters you muſt take the <hi>Air</hi> as it is, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with it; otherwiſe if you will chuſe for the beſt, you are to conſider two things chiefly, its ſubſtance and its quality: its ſubſtance muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, pure and not corrupted, not putrify'd. A ſerene, pure, perſpicuous and temper'd <hi>Air,</hi> that exhilerates the heart, illuſtrates the Spirits, and makes the blood apt to be diſtributed through the whole Body; ſo that there is nothing almoſt more healthful for the Body of man than to live in ſuch an <hi>Air.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next the <hi>Quality of the Air,</hi> that's from the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon, &amp;c.</hi> in the <hi>Spring,</hi> eſpecially in the midſt of its extreams, the <hi>Air</hi> is hot and moiſt;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35472:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Summer,</hi> hot and dry; in <hi>Autumn,</hi> cold and dry; and in <hi>Winter,</hi> cold and moiſt; and the ſame may almoſt be ſaid of the ſeveral parts of the day; for the Morning anſwers to the <hi>Spring</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Moon</hi> changes the <hi>Air</hi> with its quarters; for the firſt quarter is like the <hi>Spring;</hi> the ſecond <hi>Summer;</hi> the third <hi>Autumn,</hi> and the laſt quarter like <hi>Winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is ſaid concerning <hi>Air,</hi> I hope will not diſpleaſe; for <hi>Air</hi> is of great concern in moſt diſeaſes; thouſands have been freed from deplorable diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by change of <hi>Air</hi> only; yet change of <hi>Air</hi> may do harm, as if one goes out of a good <hi>Air</hi> into a bad one.</p>
               <p>Next is <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance affords <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad juice; is of good or bad Concoction, little or much nouriſhment:</hi> to preſerve or recover health, Meat of good juice is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; for Diſeaſes are produced from Meats of bad juice: light food and Spices beget thin Blood, which weakens and exhauſts the ſubſtance of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; groſs begets clammy blood, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35472:30"/>our natural heat and begets fulneſs, and bad humours.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Quality</hi> hot, cold, moiſt, dry meats, do affect us with their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; the quality of Food when in health muſt be correſpondent to the temper and age of the body; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and time of the Year; but in ſickneſs contrary, to reduce it.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Quantity,</hi> we ought never to eat more than nature requires; fulneſs is the Parent of all bad humours; and faſting or a ſpae Dyet waſts the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and innate heat: and all manner of Dyet is either thin or ſparing, or groſs, or a mean; the firſt diminiſhes our faculties, the ſecond augments, the laſt preſerves them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſtome</hi> is to be kept, for 'tis a ſecond nature. For Ruſties who are us'd to groſs meat, as ſtrong <hi>Beef</hi> and <hi>Bacon;</hi> better concoct it than tenderer meats, which are rather apt to corrupt in their Stomach: therefore things we are accuſtomed to, though worſe, are better than what we are not.</p>
               <p>A regard ſhould be had to the <hi>Order</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:35472:30"/>of <hi>Dyet;</hi> ſo that Meats that are eaſie, are to be eaten before thoſe of hard Concoction, ſo moiſt Meats are to be taken before dry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meats</hi> are not to be taken out of <hi>Time;</hi> thoſe in health are to eat after exerciſe, and when their former meat is concocted; and generally at an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed hour: to ſtay longer fills the Stomach with ſharp, bad humors, and to eat before creates crudities. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect the <hi>Time</hi> of the Year, in <hi>Winter</hi> 'tis beſt to eat more and drink leſs; let your meat and drink be hot and drying; as Roaſt-meat, and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger drings; in the <hi>Spring</hi> eat leſs, but drink more and ſmaller drinks; and eat Boyl'd meats rather then Roaſt; and hotter than in <hi>Summer:</hi> in <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> eat little and often; in <hi>Winter</hi> otherwiſe: let the ſickly feed ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for cold dulls weak Stomachs: the ſame is to be ſaid of the <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Age;</hi> for we muſt eat more ſparingly in an hot, then in a cold Country; ſo Young men require more Meat than Old; ſo Childrens Dyet
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35472:31"/>muſt be moiſt, leſt their growth be hindred by a dry one: to Boys hot and dry, a cold Dyet will be beſt; Boyl'd meat rather then Roaſt, much drink, but not ſtrong; Young men from 14 to 25 of a temperate Conſtitution, require a temperate Dyet.</p>
               <p>But here comes a queſtion, <hi>How oft we are to eat in a day?</hi> which I think in general cannot be decided, becauſe of ſo numerous variety of tempers; for <hi>Phlegmatic</hi> people, who are beſt able to faſt, once a day may be enough; the <hi>Coleric,</hi> who eaſily is hurt by faſting, he may eat oftner but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; they may Breakfaſt, Dine and Sup, but ſoberly: let the <hi>Sanguine</hi> keep a mean in all things: let the <hi>Melancholic</hi> may take ſomething thrice a day, whereby they may moiſten their dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Moſt certain our fore-fathers were far more ſparing than us; and ſo prolong'd their lives, and were active, ſtrong, beautiful, tall: But yet we muſt not believe they fed only on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns,</hi> as Poetical Fables relate: but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35472:31"/>all manner of Fruits, Pulles and fleſh: for Holy Writ tells us, after our firſt Parents were caſt out of Paradiſe, they tilled the Earth, and ſacrific'd Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims, whoſe fleſh and intrails they probably fed upon. And 'tis moſt certain that <hi>Intemperance is the Nurſe of Phyſitians; and that more periſh by Gluttouy than the Sword.</hi> Our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors ſays <hi>Galen</hi> more rarely were ſick, becauſe they liv'd more temperately. <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ſays, Women, and Eunuchs were not troubled with the Gout; but neither are free from it now; becauſe of their Gluttony. Wherefore 'tis beſt to obſerve that Golden precept of <hi>Socrates, we ought to eat to live, and not to live to eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>At which repaſt is moſt to be eaten, Dinner or Supper?</hi> This queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath been formerly ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, that ſome of the <hi>Italian</hi> Phyſicians have written whole books, thereon. I am of opinion <hi>that it is more healthful to ſup ſparingly.</hi> Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the frequent experience of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an infinite of men, who have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35472:32"/>receiv'd the greateſt benefits from a light Supper; the Stomach is leaſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd, and ſo ſleep muſt be more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; Secondly, the matter is preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereby they are obnoxous to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxions, Rheumatiſms, Gouts, Dropſies, Vertigoes,</hi> &amp;c. that eat large Suppers. Thirdly, from a ſparing Supper fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows more alacrity the next day; and concoction is better perfected, and ſo grevious obſtructions are prevented, with many more diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Another queſtion may be, <hi>Whether Meals are to begun with Meat or Drink? Liquids or Solids?</hi> And here I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that we ſhould begin with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids; becauſe they are ſooneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted; and then the concoction of Meat in the Stomach is performed after the manner that crude Fleſh is in the pot; whece, the Prince of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> compares this firſt coction to the boyling of Meat in the Pot; but we firſt put water into the Pot, then fleſh: which is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of Broths and ſuch liquid things, not Wine, or ſtrong Ale or Beer, for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35472:32"/>they offend the Nervous parts of our bodies, and ſo cauſe <hi>Gouts</hi> and <hi>Scurvey</hi> humours; and <hi>fluctuations</hi> in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, whence is all coction diſturb'd: (for this it was that <hi>Galen</hi> would have meat precede;) drink Broths firſt then ſome ſolid ſubſtance, then to drink, that all may be equally mixt in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, remembring what <hi>Schola Salerni,</hi> ſays, <hi>Inter prandendum ſit ſaepe parumque bibendum.</hi> But not to eat any crude Fruit after Meals, as 'tis too common, but either boyl'd, roaſted, bak'd or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd may be moderately taken.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Drink,</hi> that appeaſes Thirſt, and is the Vehicle of Food, if it be purely drink, as Water; it may be liberally drank, if the bodies be ſtrong and firm; but if weak, ſparingly, and the oftner. We here in <hi>England</hi> drink ſmall Beer generally, and the poor fort ith' Country drink <hi>Whey</hi> and <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-milk,</hi> &amp;c. of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>Thus far of <hi>Dyet</hi> in <hi>General;</hi> now in particular, the firſt thing that occurs s <hi>Bread,</hi> the beſt is made of Wheat, leven'd better then unleaven'd. Now
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35472:33"/>as there are ſeveral ſorts of Wheat; ſo the <hi>Bread</hi> is of different nature where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is made; that which is made of the pure meal is beſt; the next is that with <hi>Meal</hi> and <hi>Bran;</hi> that made of all <hi>Bran</hi> is for Dogs; always remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to put a convenient quantity of <hi>Salt</hi> into your <hi>Bread,</hi> againſt obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bread</hi> made of <hi>Rye</hi> nouriſhes leſs, and is not ſo eaſily concocted; but mixt with <hi>Wheat</hi> 'tis better, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords a moderate nouriſhment. <hi>Barley bread,</hi> nouriſhes leaſt of all; yet it drys and cleanſes, and is the ſame with <hi>Oats,</hi> by all which you may eaſily conjecture at the nature of <hi>Miſcelane.</hi> The old Proverb is, <hi>An Egg of an hour, bread of a day, and Wine of a year.</hi> The <hi>Crumb</hi> affords the beſt juice, and is of eaſier concoction than the <hi>Curſt,</hi> which is dryer, and <hi>Schola Salerni</hi> ſays, <hi>Ne c medes cruſtam coleram quia gignit aduſtam,</hi> then cut away the burnt <hi>Cruſt:</hi> yet the <hi>Cruſt</hi> is not ſo much to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approv'd as ſome ſuppoſe; for its a very convenient Food for thoſe of a ſtrong Stomach.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35472:33"/>
               <p>Hither are to be referr'd all kind of ſweet-Breads, which in general are but bad Food, except Biſcockt; for none of them are without their fault; among which are alſo Puddings, Paſties, Pan-cakes, Cheeſe-cakes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, and many ſuch like, <hi>Quelque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſe,</hi> hony'd, ſugar'd, milky'd, egg'd: all bak'd Meats are hurtful to the Stomach and Liver, ſeeing they moſt manifeſtly heat, obſtruct and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the inward parts.</p>
               <p>The next are <hi>Fruits;</hi> of which this may be affirm'd in general, that they moiſten and cool much; nouriſh little, yet ſome more, ſome leſs. All Fruits almoſt are endued with ſome bad qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and beget winds and ſerous, thin humours, and are very hurtful to diſtempers proceeding from obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and putrid Fevers: of Fruits that will not keep long, and are ſoon rotten, the moiſter are to be choſen, and eaten in the firſt courſe; ſuch are <hi>Prunes, Cherries, Grapes,</hi> but the more ſolid and ſuch as bind more, and will not be rotten ſo ſoon, are to be eaten at
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35472:34"/>the ſecond courſe; among which are <hi>Quinces, Pears, Apples, Nuts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It is a moſt certain rule, that all Fruits that may be boyl'd, bak'd, or roaſted, beget bad juice, if eaten crude.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Melons, Corcumbers, Pompions,</hi> they may in ſome meaſure conduce to hot Stomachs and Choleric perſons, for they refreſh and moiſten much; but they beget thick, cold juice, and of hard concoction; Hiſtorians make mention of perſons of great renown that dyed by eating <hi>Melons:</hi> and <hi>Pears, Quinces, Medlars, Services,</hi> &amp;c. ought not to be eaten by healthful people, but after meals; and then but in ſmall quantity, to ſtrengthen the Stomach; <hi>Filbirds</hi> may be allow'd, as being of a temperate nature; <hi>Cheſnuts</hi> beget thick Blood, Wind, and not eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted.</p>
               <p>No <hi>Pulſes</hi> are much to be commended; for <hi>Beans</hi> green are windy, diſturb the ſenſes, cauſe Dreams, and are of a a thick juice, hard of concoction and not much nouriſhing; <hi>Primroſe</hi> ſays,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35472:34"/>they beget ſerous blood; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but dry'd they refrigrate, dry, and deterge alſo, apply'd in Pultiſes: <hi>Peaſe</hi> are of the ſame nature. <hi>Rice</hi> and <hi>French</hi>-Barly are the moſt excellent of all <hi>Pulſes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they nouriſh moſt, and breed ſeweſt Excrements: both moderately ſtrengthen the Stomach, and are not of bad concoction: <hi>Ciches</hi> or <hi>Vitches,</hi> nouriſh more than <hi>Peaſe,</hi> and diſcharge the reins, by their Diuretic faculty, and therefore are thought to be profitable to thoſe that are obnoxious to the Stone in the Kidnies: But it is beſt to uſe them ſparingly, nor without the <hi>Phyſician</hi>'s advice; for by the undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet uſing of them, neither few nor light ſymptoms may enſue; as alſo from the untimely uſe of any other Diuretics.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herbs</hi> come next to be handled; In general all <hi>Herbs</hi> nouriſh little and are rather endued with altering quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for they heat, cool, dry, and moiſten what way ſoever us'd. <hi>Galen</hi> extolls <hi>Letuce</hi> above all herbs; as endued with nouriſhing juice, but very
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35472:35"/>cooling; and cauſing ſleepineſs: Next in coolneſs are <hi>Sorrel, Cichory, Porce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> &amp;c. which may be profitably us'd dayly; Among hot <hi>Herbs</hi> are <hi>Sage, Thyme, Savory, Penyroal, Majoram, Roſemary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Roots</hi> are by all eſteem'd windy Food, ſome nouriſh more than others.</p>
               <p>Now the Food we receive from <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals</hi> may be reduced to <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Eggs</hi> in general: and <hi>Fleſh</hi> to <hi>Fiſh, Birds,</hi> or <hi>four footed Beaſts.</hi> Of <hi>Fiſh</hi> thoſe that live about the Rocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are moſt commended; <hi>Sea-fiſh</hi> are better than <hi>River-Fiſh;</hi> ſtanding Pools worſt. All <hi>Freſh-fiſh</hi> beget <hi>Phlegm;</hi> are eaſily corrupted; dry'd and ſalt are of hard digeſtion, and burn the blood. The beſt are <hi>Trouts, Pike, Sole, Roach, Carp, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot;</hi> then <hi>Mackrel Perch, Skait, Eeles:</hi> for <hi>Tench, Crab fiſh, Lobſters,</hi> are of difficult coction; ſo laſt in goodneſs; <hi>Salmon</hi> is to be eaten with moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Fiſh,</hi> boil'd leſs good, fry'd bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, roaſted beſt becauſe dryeſt. In general the Male better then the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35472:35"/>young (but not the very leaſt) better then old; notwithſtanding the old Proverb, <hi>Young Fleſh, and old Fiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Birds,</hi> &amp;c. young better then old, thoſe that feed upon Mountains and high grounds, are of eaſier digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than others; Tame have tenderer and moiſt Fleſh; wild harder and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: thoſe that are caſtrated are of a more pleaſant taſte than others: <hi>Birds</hi> nouriſh leſs, though ſooner concocted than four footed Beaſts. The beſt are <hi>Patriges</hi> and Mountain Birds, <hi>Cardan</hi> a a <hi>Phyſitian</hi> ſo highly extolls <hi>Patriges,</hi> if you'll believe him, that of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves he ſays they are able to cure the <hi>Pox,</hi> which he found by experience upon his own body, having, as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly confeſſes of himſelf, being infected therewith no leſs than ſeven times; next <hi>Woodcocks, Blackbirds, Doves, Pheaſants,</hi> then <hi>Chickens, Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> and <hi>Capons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Four-footed</hi> Animals, <hi>Fauns, Lambs, Pig, Weather, Veal,</hi> are beſt for taſte and nouriſhment; <hi>Porks-fleſh</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:35472:36"/>nouriſhes very much, but requires a ſtronger Stomach; <hi>Galen</hi> prefers it before all; <hi>Beef</hi> is groſſer, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets more <hi>Melancholic</hi> juice then <hi>Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> Now there are ſeveral ſorts of ways of Cooking this Fleſh; <hi>roaſting, boyling, frying, baking,</hi> &amp;c. for dry bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies boil'd is beſt, for moiſt others; Broaths are of eaſie nouriſhment being ſoon diſtributed.</p>
               <p>To this belongs <hi>Sauces</hi> and ſuch things as are uſed in preſerving of Food. As firſt <hi>Hony;</hi> hot and ſharp; <hi>Sugar</hi> comes nigheſt to it not ſo hot; more pleaſant and familiar to the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. <hi>Salt</hi> is hot and dry; and ſo are all <hi>Spices. Muſtard-ſeed</hi> is moſt hot and dry; <hi>Oyl</hi> is temperate: <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar's</hi> temper is not decided; as <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> 'tis cold; as made of Corrupt <hi>Wine,</hi> it retains ſomewhat of heat, but 'tis more cold than hot; it drys, provoks an Appetite, and ſtrengthens the Stomach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hens, Pheſants, Patriges, Turkys</hi>-Eggs are the beſt, <hi>Duck</hi> and <hi>Gooſe</hi> the worſt: beſides <hi>Eggs,</hi> we have <hi>Milk,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35472:36"/>Butter, Cheeſe, Blood</hi> from four-footed Beaſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Milk</hi> is of a diverſe temper, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Animal 'tis milk'd from. It conſiſts of a threefold ſubſtance, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh, whence <hi>Whey;</hi> thick whence <hi>Cheeſe;</hi> fatty and oily, whence <hi>Butter, Cows</hi> Milk hath moſt <hi>Butter,</hi> ſo it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes moſt, and cools leſs. <hi>Sheeps</hi> more <hi>Cheeſe</hi> ſo worſe; <hi>Aſſes</hi> moſt <hi>Whey,</hi> ſo fitteſt to cool and moiſten; <hi>Goats</hi> of a middle temper, <hi>Butter</hi> heats ſomewhat, nouriſhes little, loſens and and ſoftens: <hi>Cheeſe</hi> of thick bad juice ſo ſtopping, an Enemy to thoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Stone</hi> ith' <hi>Kidneys:</hi> ſo the Proverb is very true.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Caſeus ille bonus quem dat avara manus.</head>
                  <p>All <hi>Blood</hi> is of hard coction and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes little, <hi>Beef-blood</hi> the worſt. Thus far concerning <hi>Meat,</hi> next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Drink,</hi> was nothing but Water in the beginning of the World; if it be colour'd or ſmell, or taſte, not good;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35472:37"/>lighteſt the beſt; for weak Stomachs it may be boil'd: and becauſe few drink water alone, <hi>Barley</hi> may be boyl'd therein and ſo made <hi>Beer</hi> and <hi>Ale;</hi> ſtronger or ſmaller; ſome add <hi>Wheat, Oats</hi> and <hi>Beans;</hi> certainly 'tis the moſt healthful drink, if people would accuſtome themſelves to it; for ſo they would free themſelves from a a world of Diſeaſes got by immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate drinking <hi>Wine</hi> or ſtrong <hi>Beer,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Tremblings, Palſie, Lethargy, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, Verligo, Pains ith Head, Eyes, Gout, Stone, Dropſie, Rheumatiſms, Piles,</hi> &amp;c. for it ſtrengthens the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, cauſes an Appetite; the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> and <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Prieſts and Kings drank nothing but <hi>Water; Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> order Nurſes, Children, Students to drink <hi>Water. Demoſthenes</hi> left <hi>Wine</hi> when he came to the Bar and Pulpit; <hi>Water</hi> preſerves and quickens the ſight. <hi>Alexander Aphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus</hi> ſays in his <hi>Problems,</hi> it makes all the Senſes more lively, cools the <hi>Liver,</hi> opens the paſſages, clenſes the <hi>Reins</hi> and <hi>Bladder.</hi> Fountain and River Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are the beſt.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35472:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sleeping</hi> and <hi>Waking</hi> ought to be moderated with Prudence: <hi>Sleep</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocts Meat and Humours, corrects di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the Mind; moiſtens; <hi>Labor</hi> for the Fleſh and Joynts, <hi>Sleep</hi> for the Entralls; Night's the beſt, three hours from Supper, Day ſleep hurts, unleſs none by Night, or weary; for it makes a moiſt Brain, and breeds ſour Belch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> exceed not eight hours; lye firſt on the right ſide, then the left, nor on the Back or Face; <hi>Watching's</hi> alſo to be moderate; for immoderate produces contrary effects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Motion</hi> comprehends all exerciſe, whereof are ſeveral ſorts, <hi>Tennis,</hi> &amp;c. for the whole Body; riding for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines,</hi> walking for the <hi>Thighs,</hi> and Reading and Singing for the <hi>Lungs, &amp;c.</hi> it ſtrengthens, diſtributes, Meat: Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening; exerciſe till the Body be florid, and begin to ſweat; the ſame moderation in <hi>Reſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for things to be <hi>retein'd</hi> and <hi>voided,</hi> they help health, if thoſe be evacuated that ought, <hi>&amp; contra:</hi> things to be voided if they are retein'd hurt,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35472:38"/>as voiding of <hi>Urine,</hi> Ejections, <hi>Spittle, Hemorhair, Courſes, Seed, &amp;c.</hi> if ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd oppreſs and putrifie. So if things be voided that ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein'd, or voided in too great quantity.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the <hi>Mind,</hi> they muſt not be violent; ſo of what before as <hi>Meat,</hi> ſleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all muſt be moderate; and thus much for dyet which if minded, there would not be any need of taking ſuch uncertain remedies as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Waters; which have certainly been the utter ruin of many thouſands.</p>
                  <p>As for the many ſymptoms follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the irregular and unadviſed drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Waters, as ſuppreſſion of Urine, Dropſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> too long here to name, they are to be remedied by the Learned Phyſitian.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35472:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
